<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>vivek agarwal</title>
    <link href="http://vivek.im/feed" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://vivek.im/" />
    <updated>2013-09-01T05:21:45+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://vivek.im/</id>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[facebook, I give up]]></title>
        <author><name>Vivek Agarwal</name><uri>http://vivek.im</uri></author>
        <link href="http://vivek.im/2013/facebook"/>
        <published>2013-09-01T00:00:00+05:30</published>
        <updated>2013-09-01T05:21:45+05:30</updated>
        <id>http://vivek.im/2013/facebook</id>
        <category scheme="http://vivek.im/tag/rant/" term="rant" label="rant" />
        <category scheme="http://vivek.im/tag/facebook/" term="facebook" label="facebook" />
        <category scheme="http://vivek.im/tag/privacy/" term="privacy" label="privacy" />
        <content type="html" xml:base="http://vivek.im" xml:lang="en">
            <![CDATA[ <p>Today I gave up in my struggle against facebook. I resisted using it for almost 2 years by deactivating my account. By <cite>deactivation</cite>, I thought it meant that it was deleted; but a couple of months ago, I read the about the difference &amp; deactivation and deletion process and how facebook is retaining data for deleted accounts on HN. I tried logging into my deactivated account and voila, it resurrected. I tried looking for deletion button amidst the <a class="reference external" href="http://darkpatterns.org/">dark pattern</a>-y settings interface but all I could find was that deceiving <cite>deactivate</cite> button. I had to use google to find it out. The page said that it would take 15 days to delete my account. <a class="reference external" href="http://arstechnica.com/business/2012/02/nearly-3-years-later-deleted-facebook-photos-are-still-online/">I knew it won't be erased</a>. <a class="reference external" href="http://www.zdnet.com/blog/igeneration/facebook-does-not-erase-user-deleted-content/4808">Ever</a>. Just a delete flag toggled to True. Still I went ahead to make sure that I couldn't come back even if I wanted to.</p>
<p>Now, my startup is very much based around social interaction. I thought I could develop it without myself ever being the user of it. But I was plain wrong. Apart from that, I needed to contact some people and the only accessible &amp; convenient platform for doing that is facebook. I regretted deleting my account and decided to use the same email address that I had for previous account. Then suddenly, I was crept out the moment I submitted the signup form. Facebook suggested 8 people on the next page, all of whom were friends of my previous account. Its a clear sign that my data was not erased at all. Past a couple of page, again I was suggested over 20 people all of whom I knew. It's just been a couple of hours now since I caved in and 3 of my friends have already added me. Oh facebook, I must applaud your hard-working engineers; the system so quick to suggest me to my friends. And Zuck, I didn't knew you loved me so much that you couldn't let my account die. I was such a <a class="reference external" href="http://www.theatlanticwire.com/technology/2010/05/report-zuckerberg-called-facebook-users-who-trust-him-dumb/24459/">dumbfuck</a> for deleting my account.</p>
<p>It's not only the <a class="reference external" href="http://translate.google.com/translate?sl=no&amp;tl=en&amp;js=n&amp;prev=_t&amp;hl=en&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.vg.no%2Fnyheter%2Finnenriks%2Fartikkel.php%3Fartid%3D10104089&amp;act=url">privacy reasons</a> for which I loathe facebook so much. It's that it gradually takes over a significant part of your life. The notifications which tell you how much you're loved by others. You start craving for it. Eyeballs always checking on that tab that has been open for last 4 hours. Hitting the poor F5 as has you can. The <a class="reference external" href="http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Repetitive%20refresh%20syndrome">repetitive refresh syndrome</a>.</p>
<p>My days of digital peace are over.</p>
<p>/rant</p>
]]>
        </content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[My take on Ghost in the Shell]]></title>
        <author><name>Vivek Agarwal</name><uri>http://vivek.im</uri></author>
        <link href="http://vivek.im/2013/ghost-in-the-shell"/>
        <published>2013-08-04T00:00:00+05:30</published>
        <updated>2013-08-04T06:44:20+05:30</updated>
        <id>http://vivek.im/2013/ghost-in-the-shell</id>
        <category scheme="http://vivek.im/tag/anime/" term="anime" label="anime" />
        <category scheme="http://vivek.im/tag/philosophy/" term="philosophy" label="philosophy" />
        <category scheme="http://vivek.im/tag/gits/" term="GitS" label="GitS" />
        <content type="html" xml:base="http://vivek.im" xml:lang="en">
            <![CDATA[ <p>Today I saw <a class="reference external" href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0113568/">Ghost in the Shell</a> movie and I have to say that it is one of the greatest piece of art I've ever encountered. I've also seen 10 (of total 26) episodes of <a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghost_in_the_Shell:_Stand_Alone_Complex">Ghost in the Shell - Stand Alone Complex</a>. The movie is set during 2029 in futuristic Japan. Human augmentation is possible, human brain can directly interface with computers and yes, it can be hacked as well. Although I think this will take a bit longer to achieve in our reality, everything thing else in the movie seems very realistic. The plot was a bit unclear to me due to watching with English subtitles and also being unable to retain Japanese character names in my head. At the center of the series is <a class="reference external" href="http://ghostintheshell.wikia.com/wiki/Public_Security_Section_9_(organization)">Section 9</a>, a top secret division of Japanese government that deals with espionage, terrorism and other high profile incidents. The main character <a class="reference external" href="http://ghostintheshell.wikia.com/wiki/Motoko_Kusanagi">Major Motoko Kusanagi</a> who is a cyborg, leads the team. Some team members are completely cyborg like her while some are mostly human.</p>
<p>The series throws a lot of philosophical questions at you. One of biggest being related to <a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ship_of_Theseus">Theseus's paradox</a> and <a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sorites_paradox">Sorites paradox</a>. Theseus's paradox questions whether an object which has had all its components replaced remains fundamentally the same object. Regarding Sorites paradox, I will quote Wikipedia:</p>
<blockquote>
A typical formulation involves a heap of sand, from which grains are individually removed. Under the assumption that removing a single grain does not turn a heap into a non-heap, the paradox is to consider what happens when the process is repeated enough times: is a single remaining grain still a heap? (Or are even no grains at all a heap?) If not, when did it change from a heap to a non-heap?</blockquote>
<p>Ghost in the Shell asks the very same question. Cells in our body wither away and new ones replace them. What if each part of our body is gradually replaced by its cybernetic counterpart? When even the brain is replaced but contains all the previous data? We need to define how we are going to compare these two states. In my opinion, a person is defined by his thoughts and not his body. Body is nothing more than a chassis that houses the brain. Yes, physical body is a part of one's identity just like a person's name, sexuality, nationality, etc. And of course, the body needs to be takes care of if the brain is to survive. An infant is no longer the same physically when he turns into an adult. Much of his body cells are replaced and is grown up with 'foreign' material (food). In the above scenario with cyborg body containing same brain data, it can be said that they are both completely same person. But a real transformation happens when a person's thoughts change, no matter what the physical form is. During the movie's ending, Motoko and an artificial consciousness character <a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puppet_Master_(Ghost_in_the_Shell)#Puppeteer.2FPuppet_Master">Puppet Master</a> merge their minds (essentially databases) together and the end result is the change in Motoko's character.</p>
<img alt="/static/gits/1.jpg" src="/static/gits/1.jpg" />
<p>The next question being the difference between human and artificial consciousness. The artificial consciousness character <cite>Puppet Master</cite> in the movie, on being said that <cite>it</cite> is merely a program designed to self-preserve, replies-</p>
<blockquote>
It can also be argued that your DNA is nothing more than a program designed to preserve itself. Life is like a nodal point born in a overwhelming sea of information.</blockquote>
<p>The point <cite>he</cite> just made is pretty solid. We like to believe that there is something super-natural that sets us apart from anything that is non-flesh-n-blood. And yes, I'm using <cite>he</cite> even though he is not an organic being. Even out of the that context, it being just a character in a movie, I will continue to use the same term.</p>
<p><a class="reference external" href="http://www.simulation-argument.com/">We can't even be sure whether we are living in a simulation.</a> Even if we are, it wouldn't make much difference to me. I would like to quote <a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agent_Smith">Agent Smith</a> from <a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Matrix">The Matrix</a> -</p>
<blockquote>
Illusions, Mr. Anderson. Vagaries of perception. The temporary constructs of a feeble human intellect trying desperately to justify an existence that is without meaning or purpose.</blockquote>
<p>One thing that irked me about GitS series was the usage of the term <a class="reference external" href="http://ghostintheshell.wikia.com/wiki/Ghosts_&amp;_Shells">Ghost</a> in it. I think it means (in movie's context) an individual's personality, identity and even what is called soul. On many occasions, it was shown as some super-natural power. I disliked how the ones without ghosts were discriminated against for something that can be theoretically easily provided.</p>
<p>Ghost in the Shell was so thought provoking that it made me spill my thoughts onto here. Though there doesn't goes a day without me pondering on the same subject.</p>
<img alt="/static/gits/2.jpg" src="/static/gits/2.jpg" />
]]>
        </content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[About BF3 Server Browser I wrote]]></title>
        <author><name>Vivek Agarwal</name><uri>http://vivek.im</uri></author>
        <link href="http://vivek.im/2013/bf3-server-browser"/>
        <published>2013-04-15T00:00:00+05:30</published>
        <updated>2013-04-15T18:08:04+05:30</updated>
        <id>http://vivek.im/2013/bf3-server-browser</id>
        <category scheme="http://vivek.im/tag/games/" term="games" label="games" />
        <category scheme="http://vivek.im/tag/python/" term="python" label="python" />
        <content type="html" xml:base="http://vivek.im" xml:lang="en">
            <![CDATA[ <p>Recently I wrote a <a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/vivekagr/bf3sb">Battlefield 3 server browser application</a> in Python. With over <a class="reference external" href="http://battlelog.battlefield.com/bf3/soldier/mpheus/stats/372749077/">330 hours logged</a> in Battlefield 3, I think its fair to say that I play it a lot (though not much since I found programming to be more fun). I'm on a 512kbps connection with the country's worst ISP so I always have to look for servers with lowest ping time. Half of the times, I'm unable to play and keep getting either timed out or kicked out of servers for having high ping. And being on a slow connections creates another problem. Battlefield 3's web browser based server browser takes too long (10-30 seconds) to load and then the ping function isn't called for some reason. So, I always had to copy the server IP addresses and manually ping them via command prompt.</p>
<p>I started learning Python in January 2013, so I thought of using my newly acquired skills to do myself some good. I tried implementing the ping function with the help of <a class="reference external" href="http://docs.python.org/2/library/subprocess.html">subprocess</a> module. But routing each request via different processes and parsing out the result was very slow and inefficient. I looked for pure ping implementation in Python but couldn't find any and eventually forgot about this idea. After a couple of weeks, I came across <a class="reference external" href="https://gist.github.com/pklaus/856268">this gist</a> and began working on the project. First, I made a <a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/mitsuhiko/flask">Flask</a> based interface over the core functions and it worked well. But running the python script each time over the cmd felt cumbersome (even more so on Windows). Then I remembered getting a Python GUI development course coupon on <a class="reference external" href="http://redd.it/14453f">this reddit thread</a> months ago. Bogdan Milanovich gave away <a class="reference external" href="https://www.udemy.com/python-gui-programming">his course</a> for free. I started going through the videos and then worked on making the GUI. The course videos were fantastic.</p>
<p><a class="reference external" href="http://qt-project.org/wiki/Category:LanguageBindings::PySide">PySide</a> (Python bindings to the Qt framework) was used during the course. There also exists <a class="reference external" href="http://www.riverbankcomputing.com/software/pyqt/intro">PyQt</a> which is more mature than PySide and similar to it. The major difference being the license, PySide is under LGPL and PyQt under GPL (discussed in-depth <a class="reference external" href="http://www.devilsan.com/1/post/2013/01/choosing-between-pyside-or-pyqt-license-consideration.html">here</a>). I didn't spend time choosing one between the two and just went with the course's choice. Qt Designer (part of Qt Creator) is an amazing tool to quickly design the GUI which can then be used in any language which has bindings for Qt. I could have used it to ease the process and just incorporated it with previously written core part, but I chose to code everything by hand. Having recently learned Python, I wanted to write as much as I could in it and also, I wanted to get familiar with Qt. Even though PySide is not that mature and parts of it's documentation are incomplete, it wasn't that hard to find the answers. For most of the queries, I got back the answer for PyQt and C++ versions, but since the classes and methods are very similarly named, it was not a problem. This <a class="reference external" href="http://www.codinguser.com/2012/07/i-miss-qt-or-what-cute-documentation-looks-like/">blog post</a> praises About and describes why Qt rocks. I also tried TkInter and wxPython GUI frameworks but PySide felt much better than both of these.</p>
<p>For showing the results, I used the Jinja2 template I earlier made for the Flask based interface. I couldn't find any good way to show the result within the application itself. Using the table widgets provided by Qt wasn't good enough. Also, one would still need to open browser to join the game server. So why not just show the result in the browser itself and reduce the distance between the result page and server join page.</p>
<p>For freezing a python script into a standalone executable, there are quite a few options like <a class="reference external" href="http://cx-freeze.sourceforge.net/">cx_Freeze</a>, <a class="reference external" href="http://www.py2exe.org/">py2exe</a> and <a class="reference external" href="http://www.pyinstaller.org/">PyInstaller</a>. PyInstaller seemed to be the best choice for freezing Qt applications. It produced the smallest sized exe, of around 11MB containing the script, Python itself and necessary Qt files. I will cover this part in depth in another post. With cx_Freeze, freezing especially Qt apps isn't straightforward. I wasn't able to properly do it after spending an hour and still the output exe was well over 30MB in size (I assume that even after getting it to work, it wouldn't shrink down).</p>
<p>And just to make it a complete package, I used <a class="reference external" href="http://www.jrsoftware.org/isinfo.php">Inno Setup</a> to make the installer. Finally, to distribute the binaries I uploaded them to SourceForge.net. I really wish Github had the option to upload binaries. Well they had but <a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/blog/1302-goodbye-uploads">it was deprecated</a>. I hope it comes back in future.</p>
<p>One thing I learned is that it takes more effort to design the user interface than to build the core part of a software. Actually I learned many other things too while making this. It can scrape data for and ping 500 servers under a minute on my sluggish connection. I don't think anyone uses it except myself and a friend of mine but still I'm incredibly proud of it.</p>
<p>Source and download links are available at - <a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/vivekagr/bf3sb">https://github.com/vivekagr/bf3sb</a></p>
]]>
        </content>
    </entry><entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World]]></title>
        <author><name>Vivek Agarwal</name><uri>http://vivek.im</uri></author>
        <link href="http://vivek.im/2013/hello-world"/>
        <published>2013-04-03T00:00:00+05:30</published>
        <updated>2013-04-08T15:51:05+05:30</updated>
        <id>http://vivek.im/2013/hello-world</id>
        <category scheme="http://vivek.im/tag/blogging/" term="blogging" label="blogging" />
        <content type="html" xml:base="http://vivek.im" xml:lang="en">
            <![CDATA[ <p>So, I finally decided to start blogging. The obvious solution was to use Wordpress as I have in the past for other sites. But I wanted to try something else this time. Github Pages for free hosting was very enticing but that can only serve static files which meant I had to use a static blog generator.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</a> is kind of popular these days with a lot of features. But it&#39;s written in Ruby (which I don&#39;t know at this point) and I&#39;m a Python guy, so I looked for other options so that I can easily modify the code to suit my needs. <a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican">Pelican</a> seemed good and to try it out, I started porting my Scala notes from Evernote to markdown format. I had a few questions and Justin was out there on freenode at #pelican to assist me. It was all good, until I discovered <a href="http://nikola.ralsina.com.ar/">Nikola</a> which seemed much better and simple than Pelican. It also supported markdown format so I had to change basically nothing to try out my notes on Nikola. There were many themes to choose from and it looked wonderful. But there was no category support in Nikola. Sigh, I had to start looking for something else.</p>
<p>Fast forward a few days, I stumbled upon <a href="http://tshepang.net/favorite-pelican-themes">this post</a> while searching for themes for Pelican and Nikola. But his blog was using something else and it was looking very good. It was <a href="http://lab.lepture.com/liquidluck/">Felix Felicis</a> (in case you don&#39;t know, the <a href="http://harrypotter.wikia.com/wiki/Felix_Felicis">term</a> is from Harry Potter universe which means liquid luck potion). I had found the perfect static blog generator I was looking for. Setting it up was quick since it is not cluttered with too many useless features, straight to the point and also supports markdown format for posts.</p>
<p>The domain was hosted on a shared Hostgator account with MX entries for Google apps. To use this domain with Github, I made an A record pointing to the IP address provided by Github and the MX entries (again) on the domain registrar&#39;s end (since I wanted to get rid of dependency on Hostgator which was useless at this point).</p>
<p>Deciding to go with static blog generator in place of Wordpress sure took much longer than I anticipated but I hope it&#39;ll be worth it in the long run.</p>
]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>